<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Portal | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/portal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:25:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Adobe Flex with IBM WebSphere Portal]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/01/07/integrating-adobe-flex-with-ibm-websphere-portal/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-07T14:48:44-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/01/07/integrating-adobe-flex-with-ibm-websphere-portal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Integrating Flex into portals has always been an interesting topic for enterprise developers.  Other than <a href="http://www.jamesward.com/2006/11/02/flex-your-oracle-portal/">a blog</a> I did a while back there hasn't been much information out there about how to get Flex apps into portals.  But I just read a great article on IBM developerWorks about <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/websphere/library/techarticles/0911_el-hadik/0911_el-hadik.html?S_TACT=105AGX10&amp;S_CMP=LP">Integrating Adobe Flex with IBM WebSphere Portal</a>.  It's a great read for enterprise developers looking to combine Flex and WebSphere Portal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIA Weeky #41: Portals and RIAs - Flex and Open Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2009/02/03/ria-weeky-41-portals-and-rias-flex-and-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-03T12:30:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2009/02/03/ria-weeky-41-portals-and-rias-flex-and-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I was able to be a guest speaker on the <a href="http://www.riaweekly.com">RIA Weekly</a> podcast.  In <a href="http://www.riaweekly.com/2009/01/30/riaweekly041">the episode</a> <a href="http://www.redmonk.com/cote/">Coté</a> and I talked about RIAs in Portals, Flex and Open Source, and other various topics.  Give it a listen and let us know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flex Your Oracle Portal]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2006/11/02/flex-your-oracle-portal/"/>
    <updated>2006-11-02T11:11:19-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2006/11/02/flex-your-oracle-portal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week while many of us were gallivanting around Vegas at MAX, Oracle was holding their OpenWorld conference in San Francicso.  Unfortunately I wasn't able to be in two places at once, so I didn't attend OpenWorld.  But I did have the opportunity of building a Flex demo for one of the Oracle keynotes.  I really just took a few of our sample applications and portalized them.  You can see the end result on <a href="http://portalstandards.oracle.com/portal/page/portal/FlexPG/Flex%20Demo%201/Tab">Oracle's Portlet Testing Site</a>.  One cool thing to point out is that the portlets are actually remote portlets being served via Oracle's JPDK.  In case you want to play around with these portlets in your own portal, the provider url is: <a href="http://www.jamesward.org:8888/flexportlets/providers/flex_portlets">http://www.jamesward.org:8888/flexportlets/providers/flex_portlets</a></p>

<p>Also be sure to read the Oracle Press Release:
<a href="http://www.oracle.com/corporate/press/2006_oct/openworldsf06-06.html">Oracle and Adobe Collaborate to Enable Enterprise Rich Client Development</a></p>

<p>And an article I helped write: <a href="http://www.adobe.com/go/flexportalintegration">Providing Rich Portlets with Adobe Flex</a></p>

<p>In the past 2 months Flex was used in a keynote at Intel's developer conference, a Flex application took second place at SAP TechED's Demo Jam, and most recently Oracle did the keynote Flex demo at OpenWorld!  Enterprise software continues to be transformed by Flex!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
