<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JBoss | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/jboss/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:07:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating Flex and Java EE with JBoss]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/03/08/integrating-flex-and-java-ee-with-jboss/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-08T08:23:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/03/08/integrating-flex-and-java-ee-with-jboss</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Flex and Java have always fit together very nicely.  Connecting from Flex to a Java back-end is pretty straightforward whether you are using plain old Java beans, Spring beans, or EJB session beans.  I've created a video and some <a href="http://code.google.com/p/jbossflex/">sample code</a> that shows you how to connect Flex to a Java EE system using BlazeDS.  This video walks though a real-time collaborative Whiteboard application that runs in the browser, on the desktop, and on mobile devices.  Check out the video and let me know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flex and Seam at JavaOne 2008]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2008/05/02/flex-and-seam-at-javaone-2008/"/>
    <updated>2008-05-02T10:57:43-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2008/05/02/flex-and-seam-at-javaone-2008</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There will be numerous mini-sessions happening this year at the Adobe booth at JavaOne 2008.  I'll be doing a "Building High Performance RIAs" session and a "The Open Source RIA Stack" session.  <a href="http://graphics-geek.blogspot.com/">Chet Haase</a> will be doing a "Filthy Rich [Flex] Clients" session.  Bob Tierney will be doing a "LiveCycle Data Services" session and a "LiveCycle and BEA" session.  <a href="http://technoracle.blogspot.com/">Duane Nickull</a> will also be doing sessions.  We also have one guest presenter, Igor Polevoy from <a href="http://exadel.com/">Exadel</a>, who will be demonstrating Flex and Seam integration with <a href="http://flamingo.exadel.com/">Flamingo</a>.  Igor's session will be at 1pm on Tuesday.  Other session times are TBD - so stop by the booth on Tuesday to pickup a schedule.  Also, make sure that you come to the Filthy Rich [Flex] Clients session with Stephan Jansen (of <a href="http://www.parleys.com/display/V21Beta/Home">Parleys.com</a> and <a href="http://javapolis.com">JavaPolis</a>), Chet Haase, and myself which precedes the Adobe party on Wednesday night.  Stop by the booth to pickup an invite.  See you there!</p>

<p><strong><em>  Quick Update: Duane will also be doing a hands-on Flex and AIR session at CommunityOne on Monday at noon.  I'll be doing a Lightning Talk at noon and hanging out with the RedMonk folks at CommunityOne.  </em></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
