<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Intuit | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/intuit/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-13T00:32:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intuit Cloud Webinar on January 14]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/01/06/intuit-cloud-webinar-on-january-24/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-06T09:03:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/01/06/intuit-cloud-webinar-on-january-24</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Edit: Whoops.  It's on the 14th not the 24th!</p>

<p>Intuit's Cloud / Platform as a Service (PaaS) technology called the Intuit Partner Platform (IPP) has quickly matured into a first class Client + Cloud solution.  Building a custom user interface with IPP is done through Flex.  This is a perfect combination and opens many opportunities for developers to build and sell apps into Intuit's extensive ecosystem.  They are doing a <a href="https://www1.gotomeeting.com/register/152420656">Webinar on January 14</a> about what's new in IPP v2.4.  This is a great opportunity to learn more about how you can build apps for the IPP with Flex.  Definitely a session not to miss!
<img src="http://www.jamesward.com/wp/uploads/2010/01/ipp.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intuit Unites Flex RIAs and the Cloud]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2008/11/12/intuit-unites-flex-rias-and-the-cloud/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-12T14:03:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2008/11/12/intuit-unites-flex-rias-and-the-cloud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Normal computer users like my father know at least three software vendors: Microsoft, Adobe, and Intuit.  Microsoft is known for Windows and Office, Adobe for PDF (Reader / Acrobat), and Intuit for Quicken and QuickBooks.  Yet all three of these software vendors are changing.  All are moving in two directions concurrently: rich Internet applications and the cloud.  These two paradigm shifts are changing how developers build software but more importantly they are changing how people like my father experience and use software.</p>

<p>The future of software is services in the cloud and rich Internet application on the client.  Adobe has pulled back the curtain and given us a glimpse of this with new products like <a href="http://www.photoshop.com">photoshop.com</a> and <a href="http://www.acrobat.com">acrobat.com</a>.  Intuit is beginning to do the same with QuickBase and Flex through the <a href="http://developer.intuit.com/ipp">Intuit Partner Platform</a>. For developers this means that applications can be built with Flex and live in the cloud.  These applications can even integrate with QuickBooks.  Intuit has built an Eclipse plugin that works with Flex Builder.  This makes it extremely easy to build cloud-based Flex applications.  I've recorded two short screencasts that will walk you through how all of this works:</p>

<p><a href="/videos/intuit_quickbase_and_flex_part1.html">Part 1: Creating a QuickBase application with Adobe AIR and Flex</a></p>

<p><a href="/videos/intuit_quickbase_and_flex_part2.html">Part 2: Creating a QuickBase widget for the browser and the desktop</a></p>

<p>To get started or to read more visit <a href="http://developer.intuit.com/">Intuit's Developer website</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/quickbase_flex.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
