<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Conferences | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:25:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heroku Preso from Devoxx 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/11/29/heroku-preso-from-devoxx-2011/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-29T12:05:03-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/11/29/heroku-preso-from-devoxx-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As expected...  <a href="http://devoxx.com/display/DV11/Home">Devoxx 2011</a> rocked!  Such a fun conference with top notch sessions and people.  I presented a session on how to deploy Java, Play Framework, and Scala apps on Heroku.  <a href="http://raibledesigns.com">Matt Raible</a> did a great (and very thorough) <a href="http://raibledesigns.com/rd/entry/deploying_java_and_play_framework">write-up on my session</a>.  Thanks Matt!  Here are my slides:</p>

<p>There was also some hot news at Devoxx...  <a href="http://www.playframework.org/2.0">Play Framework 2</a> is the official web framework in the <a href="http://typesafe.com/technology/play">Typesafe Stack</a>!  And <a href="https://github.com/playframework/Play20/wiki/ProductionHeroku">Heroku already supports Play 2</a>!  Awesome stuff.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heroku at Devoxx 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/11/14/heroku-at-devoxx-2011/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-14T06:53:29-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/11/14/heroku-at-devoxx-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://devoxx.com">Devoxx</a> is one of my favorite conferences of the year so I'm lucky to be presenting there again this year.  This <a href="http://devoxx.com/display/DV11/Conf+Day+4">Thursday at noon</a> I'll be presenting about Heroku and how to <a href="http://devoxx.com/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=5015973">deploy Java, Play Framework, and Scala apps on the cloud</a>.  Hopefully see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dreamforce 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/08/10/dreamforce-2011/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-10T10:15:24-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/08/10/dreamforce-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm very excited to be presenting at <a href="http://www.salesforce.com/dreamforce/DF11/">Dreamforce</a> (salesforce.com's anual conference) this year!  On Thursday, September 1, from 1:15 pm to 2:15 pm I will be presenting:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Developing Java Cloud Apps</strong>
The cloud makes it easy to deploy highly scalable apps in an instant. This session will walk you through the steps to build your first Java app for the cloud. You'll also learn best practices for building mission-critical and horizontally scalable Java cloud apps.</p></blockquote>

<p>Then on Friday, September 2, from 10:00 am to 11:00 am I will be hosting a panel discussion:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Fireside Chat: Java on the Cloud</strong>
Come join the Java on the cloud product managers, architects, and experts for a casual, unscripted chat to find out how Java developers can best take advantage of the cloud. The session will be a mix of preselected and audience-provided questions. So bring all your tough, interesting, and quirky questions to this Fireside Chat.</p></blockquote>

<p>I hope to see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programming Summer Camp 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/06/29/programming-summer-camp-2011/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-29T15:14:16-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/06/29/programming-summer-camp-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few years I've attended a bunch of geek/coder events in the Colorado Mountains.  It always surprises me how much I can learn by getting away, being around some really smart people, and writing code with them.  So I'm incredibly excited to be attending <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/programmingsummercamp/">The Programming Summer Camp 2011</a> this summer in Crested Butte, Colorado!</p>

<p>At the summer camp you can choose which campsite to hangout in.  Or if you want, you can create your own campsite!  I'll probably spend most of my time in the Scala campsite.  But I look forward to mingling in some of the other campsites as well.</p>

<p>It's like I'm a kid again - getting all excited about going to camp!  But I really hope you all can join me July 25 - 29 in Crested Butte, Colorado for <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/programmingsummercamp/">The Programming Summer Camp 2011</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Upcoming Flex Sessions in Atlanta - DevNexus and Atlanta Flex User Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/03/09/my-upcoming-flex-sessions-in-atlanta-devnexus-and-atlanta-flex-user-group/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-09T10:53:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/03/09/my-upcoming-flex-sessions-in-atlanta-devnexus-and-atlanta-flex-user-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a few weeks I'll be speaking in Atlanta at <a href="http://www.devnexus.com/">DevNexus</a> and at the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/atlflex">Atlanta Flex User Group</a>.  On March 21, 2011 at DevNexus I have two sessions:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.devnexus.com/s/presentations#1156">AS34J - ActionScript for Java Developers</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.devnexus.com/s/presentations#1155">Rapid Mobile &amp; Tablet App Development with Spring and Flex</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>On March 22, 2011 at the Atlanta Flex User Group I will be presenting about <a href="http://www.meetup.com/atlflex/events/16734337/">Flex 4.5 - The Non-Mobile New Features</a>.</p>

<p>I hope to see you at DevNexus and at the Atlanta Flex User Group!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
