<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Oracle | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/oracle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:25:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle CRM Gadgets using Adobe AIR and Flex]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2008/11/18/oracle-crm-gadgets-using-adobe-air-and-flex/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-18T14:06:28-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2008/11/18/oracle-crm-gadgets-using-adobe-air-and-flex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oliver Marks <a href="http://blogs.zdnet.com/collaboration/?p=162/">is reporting</a> that Oracle has released five new CRM Gadgets built using Adobe AIR and Flex!  At Oracle OpenWorld 2008 I had the chance to record a video of these new gadgets.  Check it out:</p>

<p>This is a great innovation in the usually boring CRM software space.  Great job Oracle!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle Open World 2008: Oracle + Flex = Happy Users]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2008/09/25/oracle-flex-happy-users/"/>
    <updated>2008-09-25T10:34:41-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2008/09/25/oracle-flex-happy-users</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week I've been at Oracle OpenWorld checking out all of the new applications Oracle has been building with Flex.  Some of these seem to be integrating Flex and ADF which is a great combination of technologies!  I've recorded videos of some of these applications which I hope to edit and publish here soon.  One of those videos will feature the <a href="https://metalink.oracle.com">new Oracle MetaLink</a>, which is a fantastic Flex application (details on <a href="http://biemond.blogspot.com/2008/07/try-new-oracle-metalink-site-build-in.html">Edwin Biemond's blog</a>).</p>

<p>It's great to see Oracle doing amazing things with Flex!  And it's also great to see the community getting excited about the combination of Oracle technologies and Flex.  While walking around OpenWorld I noticed a random whiteboard:
<img src="http://www.jamesward.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/09/oracle_flex_happy_users.jpg" alt="Oracle + Flex = Happy Users" /></p>

<p>Three-tier client/server architectures using Oracle and Flex result in happy users! Wahoo!!!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIA Weekly 002 - More on Oracle & Flex and Java/Flex Stacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2007/12/10/ria-weeky-002-more-on-oracle-flex-and-javaflex-stacks/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-10T16:22:57-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2007/12/10/ria-weeky-002-more-on-oracle-flex-and-javaflex-stacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had the great pleasure of being invited to be a guest speaker on the <a href="http://redmonk.libsyn.com/index.php?post_id=285181">second RIA Weekly podcast</a> with <a href="http://www.redmonk.com/cote/">Coté from RedMonk</a> and <a href="http://blog.digitalbackcountry.com/">Ryan Stewart</a>.  In the podcast we discuss Oracle's recent move to Flex and RIA as well as Java and Flex.  Let me know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle Chooses Flex (part 7 - Sales Campaign)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2007/11/16/oracle-chooses-flex-part-7-sales-campaign/"/>
    <updated>2007-11-16T14:54:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2007/11/16/oracle-chooses-flex-part-7-sales-campaign</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Oracle OpenWorld on Tuesday and then on Wednesday at Larry Ellison's keynote the seventh Flex application announced at OpenWorld was demonstrated.  Like <a href="/wordpress/2007/11/15/oracle-chooses-flex-part-5-sales-prospector/">Sales Prospector</a> and <a href="/wordpress/2007/11/15/oracle-chooses-flex-part-6-sales-library/">Sales Library</a> this application, Sales Campaign, is part of the larger Oracle CRM OnDemand suite that is scheduled to go live in the first half of 2008.  The Sales Campaign application allows sales people to easily create and track the success of their campaigns.  Like all the other Flex applications Oracle showed over the past few days the interface is simple, clean, and effective.  Exactly what users want!  Great job Oracle!  Here is a photo of Sales Campaign from the Tuesday session (courtesy of Todd Ruhl - my personal photographer assistant - just kidding - Todd has been an instrumental part of educating Oracle about Flex and getting Flex adopted at Oracle):</p>

<p><img src="http://www.jamesward.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2007/11/sales_campaign.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>That's about it for this seven part series on all the new Flex projects Oracle announced at OpenWorld.  Seems like maybe we should do a recap.  Coming soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oracle Chooses Flex (part 6 - Sales Library)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2007/11/15/oracle-chooses-flex-part-6-sales-library/"/>
    <updated>2007-11-15T14:21:52-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2007/11/15/oracle-chooses-flex-part-6-sales-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second Flex application which Oracle demonstrated at Ed Abbo's keynote on Tuesday was Sales Library.  The Sales Library helps sales people organize and share their sales content.  The interface is very clean and elegant.  The transitions are smooth and useful.  Very impressive stuff!  Here is a photo of the Sales Library demo from Oracle OpenWorld (courtesy of Todd Ruhl):</p>

<p><img src="http://www.jamesward.org/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2007/11/sales_library.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Still one more Oracle Flex application left to announce.  Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
