<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Open Source | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:07:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improved Open Source Testing Tools for Flex]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/06/09/improved-open-source-testing-tools-for-flex/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-09T08:44:39-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/06/09/improved-open-source-testing-tools-for-flex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in the early days of Flex there wasn't much for doing unit testing, automated testing, performance testing, etc.  Thanks to the community there are now numerous open source testing tools for Flex.  Here are some recent updates you should definitely check out if you are building production Flex apps:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.flexunit.org/?p=62">FlexUnit 4.1 Beta 1</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://flexmonkey.org/wordpress/2010/05/11/flex-4-support-now-available-from-flexmonkey-gorilla-logic/">FlexMonkey (open source automated testing) now supports Flex 4</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://pushbuttonengine.com/2010/06/pushbutton-labs-profiler-open-sourced/">PushButton Labs Profiler for Flex</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>It's very exciting to see these community driven projects continue to improve testing for Flex apps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RIA Weeky #41: Portals and RIAs - Flex and Open Source]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2009/02/03/ria-weeky-41-portals-and-rias-flex-and-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-03T12:30:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2009/02/03/ria-weeky-41-portals-and-rias-flex-and-open-source</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I was able to be a guest speaker on the <a href="http://www.riaweekly.com">RIA Weekly</a> podcast.  In <a href="http://www.riaweekly.com/2009/01/30/riaweekly041">the episode</a> <a href="http://www.redmonk.com/cote/">Coté</a> and I talked about RIAs in Portals, Flex and Open Source, and other various topics.  Give it a listen and let us know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upcoming Conference Presentations: GeoWeb, OSCON, and LinuxWorld ]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2008/07/21/upcoming-conference-presentations-geoweb-oscon-and-linuxworld/"/>
    <updated>2008-07-21T14:17:44-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2008/07/21/upcoming-conference-presentations-geoweb-oscon-and-linuxworld</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the next few weeks I'll be presenting at a few conferences:</p>

<p><a href="http://geowebconference.org/program/workshops/workshops-tuesday">GeoWeb - Map Based RIA Development Using Adobe Flex and AIR</a> with <a href="http://technoracle.blogspot.com/">Duane Nickull</a></p>

<p><a href="http://en.oreilly.com/oscon2008/public/schedule/detail/2218">OSCON - Flex: the Open Source SDK for RIAs</a> also with Duane</p>

<p><a href="http://www.linuxworldexpo.com/live/12/conference//tracks/tracksessions//QMONYB00BILW">LinuxWorld - Building Rich Internet Applications with an Open Source Stack</a></p>

<p>I hope to see some of you at those conferences.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adobe Open Source Presentation in New York Tomorrow]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2008/05/14/adobe-open-source-presentation-in-new-york-tomorrow/"/>
    <updated>2008-05-14T15:53:36-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2008/05/14/adobe-open-source-presentation-in-new-york-tomorrow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow night I'll be presenting at the New York GNU/Linux Meetup Group about Adobe Open Source - including the Adobe Flex SDK, Mozilla Tamarin, Adobe AIR (pieces like SQLite and WebKit), and BlazeDS.  More details <a href="http://linux.meetup.com/392/calendar/7593094/">here</a>.  Hope to see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tamarin-Tracing: Mozilla's New VM for ECMAScript 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2007/12/18/qvm-mozillas-new-mobile-vm-for-ecmascript-4/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-18T18:03:25-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2007/12/18/qvm-mozillas-new-mobile-vm-for-ecmascript-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[Update: QVM was an internal Adobe codename.  The new VM's name seems to be "Tamarin-Tracing".  For more info on this new VM read the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/mozilla.dev.tech.js-engine/browse_thread/thread/e10d25db3dcb28cf#841d6253dcf2de12">announcement  by Edwin Smith</a>.  Edwin doesn't explicitly state that the VM is for mobile devices but it is hinted at.  However the research paper that Edwin references does state that this tracing type of VM is good for mobile devices.]</p>

<p>The mobile space has been heating up lately with Apple's iPhone, Google's Android, and Sun's JavaFX Mobile.  But what about all of us developing with JavaScript 2.0 / ActionScript 3.0 / ES4?  While we have been able to build for Flash Lite with Flash CS3, those of us developing with Flex haven't had an easy way to use our existing programming knowledge to build mobile applications.  Part of the reason for this is that the core language of Flex (AS3 / ES4) isn't yet supported on mobile devices.  The good news is that Adobe has just contributed a new VM targeted at mobile devices, to the Mozilla Tamarin project.  Tamarin is the open source core of Flash Player 9 and will at some point be the VM in Firefox that executes JavaScript 2.0.  More specifically AVM2 is the VM piece of Tamarin which executes ActionScript Byte Code (ABC).  ABC can be created using the soon to be open source Flex SDK's ASC compiler which turns AS3 (or ES4) into ABC.  Unfortunately AVM2 wasn't written to work well on mobile devices.  So Adobe built Tamarin-Tracing - a new VM in Tamarin which is much better suited for non-pc devices.  This is very exciting stuff!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
