<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Spring | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/spring/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:25:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Upcoming Flex Sessions in Atlanta - DevNexus and Atlanta Flex User Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/03/09/my-upcoming-flex-sessions-in-atlanta-devnexus-and-atlanta-flex-user-group/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-09T10:53:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/03/09/my-upcoming-flex-sessions-in-atlanta-devnexus-and-atlanta-flex-user-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a few weeks I'll be speaking in Atlanta at <a href="http://www.devnexus.com/">DevNexus</a> and at the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/atlflex">Atlanta Flex User Group</a>.  On March 21, 2011 at DevNexus I have two sessions:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.devnexus.com/s/presentations#1156">AS34J - ActionScript for Java Developers</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.devnexus.com/s/presentations#1155">Rapid Mobile &amp; Tablet App Development with Spring and Flex</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>On March 22, 2011 at the Atlanta Flex User Group I will be presenting about <a href="http://www.meetup.com/atlflex/events/16734337/">Flex 4.5 - The Non-Mobile New Features</a>.</p>

<p>I hope to see you at DevNexus and at the Atlanta Flex User Group!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Cross-Device Apps with Flex and Spring at the Detroit JUG]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2011/02/02/building-cross-device-apps-with-flex-and-spring-at-the-detroit-jug/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-02T07:48:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2011/02/02/building-cross-device-apps-with-flex-and-spring-at-the-detroit-jug</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On February 15, 2011 I'll be presenting at the Detroit Java User Group about <a href="http://detroitjugfebruary2011-estw.eventbrite.com/">Building Cross-Device Apps with Flex and Spring</a>.  If you live in the Detroit area then I hope to see you there!  If not, then talk to your local Java User Group leader about having me come and speak.</p>

<p>Here is the abstract for the talk:
Today, users want apps in the browser, on their desktop, phone, tablet, and TV.  Reusing code across all of these devices is now crucial for developers.  By combining Flex for the UI with Spring and Hibernate for the back-end, developers can build apps that work on a variety of devices including PCs, Android phones / tablets, the BlackBerry PlayBook tablet, iPhones, and iPads.  This session will walk developers through the steps for creating these cross-device apps with Flex and Java.</p>

<p><a href="http://detroitjugfebruary2011-estw.eventbrite.com/">Go register now!</a>  See you there!  :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My JavaOne 2010 Sessions]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/09/15/my-javaone-2010-sessions/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-15T09:07:55-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/09/15/my-javaone-2010-sessions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Next week at <a href="http://www.oracle.com/us/javaonedevelop/index.html">JavaOne 2010</a> I'll be co-presenting two sessions!  On Monday <a href="http://twitter.com/jeremyg484">Jeremy Grelle</a> and I will present "<strong>End-to-End Richness: Integrating Java EE Services to Create Engaging RIAs</strong>" at the Hilton San Francisco.  Here is the session information:
Session ID: S313939
Abstract: Flex is one of the most widely used tools for building RIAs. But how do you efficiently connect applications to diverse back-end services built on Java EE? The Spring BlazeDS Integration project has emerged as an effective solution for building a lightweight connective tissue for exposing rich Java EE services to a Flex client from any Java Servlet container. Aimed at experienced Java developers who want to make maximum use of their knowledge of Spring and Java EE to build a compelling integrated experience, this session covers:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Connecting services built with Spring and Java EE APIs (JPA, JMS, JAX-WS, and JAX-RS) to a Flex client</p></li>
<li><p>Using DI techniques to configure and expose RPC and pub/sub endpoints</p></li>
<li><p>Applying a rich security model</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Time and Location: Monday, September 20, 16:00 | Hilton San Francisco, Golden Gate 3</p>

<p>On Thursday <a href="http://gregsramblings.com/">Greg Wilson</a> and I will be present "<strong>Making Real-Time Data Come Alive</strong>".  Here is the session information:
Session ID: S313543
Abstract: Using a combination of Java, JMS, and Flash, data can be visualized in real time on a client. Real-time visualizations can be in dashboards, heat maps, charts, and numerous other interactive controls. Intended for developers looking to create applications with real-time data visualizations, this session will show how to set up a system that pushes real-time messages to a client from a Java EE server and how to create a rich internet application that renders the data. It will demonstrate how to:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Configure a Java EE system that can push JMS messages to a client in real-time or near real-time</p></li>
<li><p>Build a Flash client application that renders data from the server</p></li>
<li><p>Connect a client to messages using HTTP Streaming and HTTP Long Polling</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Time and Location: Thursday, September 23, 15:30 | Parc 55, Cyril Magnin II</p>

<p>If you are at JavaOne then I hope to see you at one of these sessions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flex 4, Hibernate 3, and Spring 3 Integration]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/06/14/flex-4-hibernate-3-and-spring-3-integration/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-14T12:58:18-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/06/14/flex-4-hibernate-3-and-spring-3-integration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ectropic.com">Jon Rose</a> and I have created a new <a href="http://refcardz.dzone.com/">DZone Refcard</a> called <a href="http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/flex-4-and-spring-3">Flex 4 and Spring 3 Integration</a>.  In the Refcard, we walk you through the steps for building RIAs with Flash Builder 4, Flex 4, BlazeDS 4, Spring 3, the Spring BlazeDS Integration, and Hibernate.  Whew!  That's a lot of pieces!  The Refcard covers simple Remoting, Flex &amp; Hibernate integration through Spring (all Java annotation driven and using the new data-centric development features in Flash Builder 4), Pub / Sub Messaging, and Flex and Spring Security.  We pack a lot into six pages!</p>

<p>If you want to see recorded presentations / screencasts of some of these things check out:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://seminars.adobe.acrobat.com/p31679079/">What's new in Flash Builder 4 for Java Developers</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.jamesward.com/2010/01/11/flash-builder-4-data-wizards-with-java-spring/">Flash Builder 4 Data Wizards with Java / Spring</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.jamesward.com/2010/01/17/flex-4-and-java-spring-hibernate-in-flash-builder-4/">Flex 4, Java, Spring, and Hibernate in Flash Builder 4</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>I hope all of this is helpful.  Let me know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[London Event Tomorrow: RIAs with Java, Spring, Hibernate, BlazeDS, and Flex]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/02/09/london-event-tomorrow-rias-with-java-spring-hibernate-blazeds-and-flex/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-09T06:33:12-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/02/09/london-event-tomorrow-rias-with-java-spring-hibernate-blazeds-and-flex</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow night, Wednesday Feburary 10 2010, I'll be speaking to the London Java Community about <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Londonjavacommunity/calendar/11801621/">RIAs with Java, Spring, Hibernate, BlazeDS, and Flex</a>.  I hope to see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
