<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: RIA | James Ward]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/categories/ria/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-12T21:25:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesward.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Ward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flex and The Cloud]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2010/01/19/flex-and-the-cloud-2/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-19T15:49:53-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2010/01/19/flex-and-the-cloud-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The combination of Flex and The Cloud is quickly becoming an IT and paradigm changing combination.  Here are a number of recently published resources for learning more about this :</p>

<ul>
<li><p>An article I wrote has been published on the online Flash &amp; Flex Developer's Magazine: <a href="http://ffdmag.com/download-1-2010">Flex and The Cloud: Is this really just Client/Server 2.0?</a></p></li>
<li><p>I'll be speaking on <a href="http://ria5280.org/calendar/event/2010/2/18/163821">Thursday, February 18 2010 at the Denver Flex User Group</a> about Flex and The Cloud</p></li>
<li><p>The <a href="http://www.adobe.com/cfusion/event/index.cfm?event=list&amp;loc=en_us&amp;type=ondemand_seminar&amp;product=&amp;interest=int_rich_internet_applications&amp;audience=&amp;sdid=EGMQU">recording of a webinar</a> I co-hosted on the new Salesforce.com Cloud platform for developers has been posted</p></li>
<li><p>Jeff Douglas has posted <a href="http://blog.jeffdouglas.com/2010/01/11/developing-apps-with-the-stratus-framework/">a video walk through</a> showing how to use the new Salesforce.com Flash Builder 4 extension for Flex + Cloud apps</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Exciting stuff!  Let me know what you think!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best and Worst Practices Building RIAs]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2009/12/01/the-best-and-worst-practices-building-rias/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-01T09:22:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2009/12/01/the-best-and-worst-practices-building-rias</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago at the <a href="http://www.web2expo.com/webexny2009/">Web 2.0 Expo in NY</a> I co-presented <em>The Best and Worst Practices Building RIAs</em> with <a href="http://www.joshholmes.com">Josh Holmes</a>.  Some would say that Josh and I evangelize competitive technologies (Silverlight and Flex).  So it's really fun for us to come together and find common ground around building great software - no matter what technology is behind it.  Here are the slides from our presentation.  Let me know what you think.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/joshholmes/best-and-worst-practices-building-ria-with-adobe-and-microsoft">Best And Worst Practices Building Ria with Adobe and Microsoft</a></p>

<p>View more <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/">presentations</a> from <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/joshholmes">Josh Holmes</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adobe and Salesforce.com Unite RIA and The Cloud]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2009/10/26/adobe-and-salesforce-com-unite-ria-and-the-cloud/"/>
    <updated>2009-10-26T09:17:03-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2009/10/26/adobe-and-salesforce-com-unite-ria-and-the-cloud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The two major trends transforming software right now are Rich Internet Applications (RIAs) and Cloud Computing / Software as a Service (SaaS or PaaS).  These trends are driven by two needs:</p>

<ul>
<li>Full client capabilities, which allow software to perform optimally and increase usability</li>
<li></li>
<li><p>Easy deployment, which allows developers to focus on business needs instead of building infrastructure</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The combination of RIA and Cloud is the future of software because it provides full client capabilities and easy deployment.  The chart below illustrates this in comparison to the other major software architectures (main-frame, client / server, and web).</p>

<p><img src="http://www.jamesward.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/RIA.png" alt="RIA" /></p>

<p>In line with these trends Adobe and Salesforce.com <a href="http://bit.ly/w29bL">announced today</a> that they are working together to unite Rich Internet Applications and The Cloud.  At the core of this announcement is a developer preview of the <a href="http://developer.force.com/flashbuilder">Adobe Flash Builder for Force.com</a> tool.  This tool enables developers to easily build intuitive user interfaces with Flex which connect to the Force.com cloud platform and Salesforce.com CRM data.  These applications can be deployed either in the browser or on the desktop using Adobe AIR.  When utilizing Adobe AIR, the applications can still function when users are disconnected.  Later, when users reconnect, the changes are synchronized with Force.com using the LiveCycle Data Services synchronization engine.</p>

<p>Being able to connect Flex applications to Salesforce.com / Force.com has been possible (and easy) since I co-created what was originally called the <a href="http://www.jamesward.com/blog/2007/04/17/the-open-source-flex-and-apollo-toolkit-for-salesforcecom/">Flex Toolkit for Apex</a>.  So while it has been possible to build Rich Cloud Applications for a few years, today's announcement is significant for a few reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Adobe and Salesforce are now officially partnered together around Rich Cloud Applications</p></li>
<li><p>Much better, officially supported developer tooling</p></li>
<li><p>Much better offline data synchronization</p></li>
</ul>


<p>It's really exciting to see how the vision of Rich Cloud Applications is becoming reality!</p>

<p>If you'd like to learn more or try out the new tooling check out these resources:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://developer.force.com/flashbuilder">Get the developer preview and watch video demos</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.adobe.com/devnet/salesforce/index.html?devcon=f1">Get inspired and see how it works</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vUsC8sdJaE0">Watch a video walk-through</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>Another great way to learn more is to sign up for a <a href="https://www.developerforce.com/events/flashbuilder_webinar/registration.php?d=70130000000EuzT">Webinar / Tech Talk</a> that I will be co-presenting.</p>

<p>Let me know what you think about this exciting new partnership and developer tooling.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Video - Drunk on Software with Matt Raible]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2009/04/07/video-drunk-on-software-with-matt-raible/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-07T11:36:15-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2009/04/07/video-drunk-on-software-with-matt-raible</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://raibledesigns.com/">Matt Raible</a> is a legend in the world of Java web applications.  In the <a href="http://www.drunkonsoftware.com/2009/04/05/episode-11-matt-raible/">latest episode</a> of <a href="http://www.drunkonsoftware.com">Drunk on Software</a> <a href="http://www.ectropic.com">Jon Rose</a> and I sit down with Matt, have a few beers, and talk geek stuff.  Matt has a lot of great insight into where software is going.  In the video we asked him what the future looks like for web frameworks.  Matt's response brought into question the future of component frameworks.  Jon and I were pretty surprised by his response.  You will have to watch the video to get the whole story.  :)  Let us know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Portable RIAs Gaining Traction]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesward.github.com/2009/04/03/portable-rias-gaining-traction/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-03T12:44:48-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesward.github.com/2009/04/03/portable-rias-gaining-traction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's great to see the concept of <a href="http://www.jamesward.com/blog/portable-rias-tutorial/">Portable RIAs</a> beginning to crop up in real world applications.  The latest one I've seen is on ESPN - allowing the user to check out the latest March Madness updates from within a PDF.  Check it out:</p>

<p><a href="http://promo.espn.go.com/espn/specialsection/adobe/"><img src="http://www.jamesward.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/portable_ria_espn.jpg" alt="Portable RIA - ESPN" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
